The year is 2025. And when it's all said
and done, we might finally be able to
call it the year of the Linux desktop.
Because if you're a developer,
especially a smart, lazy developer,
there's a new Linux distro in town
designed just for you. A dro that'll
finally let you tell your next Tinder
date. I use Arch, by the way. It's
called Omarie, and it takes the
unopinionated Arch and injects the
superior opinions of legendary developer
David Hanimire Hansen, DHH. A developer
who's richer, better looking, and more
talented than us. If you don't know who
he is, he's most famous for developing
the Ruby on Rails framework. As a former
Ruby developer myself, this community
religiously adheres to the MacBook Pro
as the one true development machine. But
Macs are expensive and riddled with
proprietary software. What if there is a
better free and open- source way to use
a computer? I just threw out my MacBook.
And in today's video, we'll find out if
Omari is the ultimate operating system
for people who code. It is September
24th, 2025, and you're watching the Code
Report. I think my mom must have taken
Tylenol when she was pregnant because I
use Windows for development. But it's
time to grow up. The most important
feature to consider when choosing a
Linux DRO is the logo because that's
what you'll be wearing on t-shirts and
ultimately getting tattooed on your
body. And I really like the Omari logo.
It looks both dangerous and nerdy at the
same time. To install it, all you have
to do is download the ISO file to a USB
stick, flash it with Bellena Etcher,
then install it to a hard drive on your
PC. I'd recommend using a new SSD drive
if possible because Omari will do disk
encryption by default and wipe
everything from a previously used drive.
From there, it'll take you through a
pretty standard setup process and then
you'll end up on this nicel looking
desktop. It uses Hyperland as the window
manager, which is a far superior Windows
manager than Microsoft Windows. It'll
automatically organize your Windows in a
beautiful way. So, you'll no longer need
multiple monitors just to develop a
website. If you're not used to it
though, at first it might feel
unintuitive because hey, there's no red
X to close this window with my mouse
because everything here is optimized for
the keyboard. Euthanize your mouse, then
hit the super key plus space to bring up
the app launcher. Unlike a regular Arch
Linux system, you'll notice that this OS
is packed with pre-installed software.
That can be both a good and bad thing.
Most people I know who use Arch do so
because they want to control every bite
on the system. And seeing all of this
bloatware is making them throw up in
their mouths right now. And if you're a
DHH hater, you'll die of cringe when you
see Base Camp and Hay pre-installed. But
that's not the target audience. It seems
like the idea behind Omari is to get
developers to stop using Mac and Windows
and start using Linux as a daily driver
by providing everything you need out of
the box. We of course have Git and
Docker, Obsidian for Markdown, Piñata
for image editing, and I'm even using
the pre-installed OBS Studio for screen
recording. And when it comes to the
terminal, you have a bunch of modern
shell tools like FZF for fuzzy finding,
rip grip to replace GP, Zoxside to
replace CD, and a bunch of other
hipstery tools to replace what you would
normally find on a GNU Linux DRO. And it
even has its own custom shell functions
to do things like image conversions. If
you're writing code though, the big
question is where will you write that
code? Well, obviously not VS Code. A
keyboard focused DRO like this could
only use Neoim. But like Arch, Neovim is
notorious for its configuration
nightmares. But here it's using the Lazy
Vim config, a preconfigured version that
gives you all the power of a modern IDE
while remaining highly customizable. But
if you're truly a lazy developer, you'll
need some AI to write your code. Well,
Arch has a massive package ecosystem
through Pac-Man and the Arch user
repository. And we can easily install
new stuff by hitting super alt space.
Find your favorite AI package like Cloud
Code and install it. It's really that
easy. Even easier than a Mac or Windows
machine. And that's coming from a
Tylenol baby. Pretty cool. But is Omari
right for you? Well, if you're already
an Arch Linux Giga Chad, you're going to
hate this thing. It's way too
opinionated, but that's the idea. If you
already hate DHH, then you're going to
hate it. And if you hate memorizing
keyboard shortcuts for everything, you
might hate it, but that shouldn't
discourage you from using Linux. Also,
try out dros like Bluefin, which comes
preconfigured with VS Code and dev
containers. Ultimately though, Omari
feels like a great new gateway drug to
get people hooked on Linux without all
the pain and suffering it takes to
configure a fully loaded system. But
speaking of the terminal, another tool
you need to know about is Code Rabbit,
the sponsor of today's video. They just
launched the Code Rabbit CLI to give you
senior level code reviews right in your
terminal. That means if you're using a
CLI based coding agent like Cloud Code,
you can just install Code Rabbit once,
then ask Claude to run it whenever you
want feedback on your uncommitted
changes or specific files. From there,
Code Rabbit flags all of the bugs and
hallucinations, then hands it back to
Claude to fix everything in the
background until the code is cleaned up
enough to pass an actual code review.
The Code Rabbit CLI is free to use, and
you can install it using the command on
screen or by checking out the link
below. This has been the Code Report.
Thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next